hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights today I have
the real pleasure of speaking to Ryan
Smith Ryan is a principal investigator
at The laua Institute for brain research
and he's the research associate
professor at oxy College of Health
Sciences at the University of Tulsa his
work focuses on the neurocomputational
mechanisms underlying emotion cognition
interactions and how they relate to
brain body interactions with special
focus on planning Information Gain and
interceptive inference he is also the
primary author of probably the best
known and most highly rated tutorial on
active inference writing it alongside KL
friston and Christopher white Ryan thank
you for giving me your time uh welcome
to the show thanks for uh thanks for
having me excited to get Talk No it's
it's an absolute pleasure it's it's
really very exciting as I said I mean
obviously I'd come across your work uh
kind of inevitably for me to have
invited you but it was actually a real
treat to sort of go back and go through
like what feels like a you've done loads
and work at this incredible velocity um
so it's been really fun to dive in and
explore this I guess what felt like a
more empirical side um because I'm
spending most of my time reading sort of
philosophy papers so it's great to see
some like traditional statistics and
some proper empirical work so so it's
been a great it's been great fun on my
part I wanted to start at kind of a
pretty broad level and and speak about
subjective well-being so you wrote this
paper in 2022 sort of grounding
subjective well-being in the parameters
and mechanisms of active
inference
um you alongside Cas Beal of uh cesp
have come up with this really nice way
of grounding uh well-being in expected
free energy but as you write in that
paper you say um while variational fre
energy can be understood to track basic
biological Fitness the this is neither
necessary nor sufficient for an
individual to report High subjective
well-being so maybe where we could start
for the audience is just
explaining why the minimization of
variational free energy is not sort of
the simple solution to obtaining High
subjective well-being sure yeah and I
mean it's a definitely a very kind of
complicated and yeah complex complex
topic jump into and it honestly depends
a little bit about the exact kind of
formalism that you're kind of working in
I mean me I almost exclusively work
within the um sort of like pomdp
formalism um associated with
decision-making and planning processes
that uh that um you know as the focus
for our tutorial and you know the focus
of the tutorial was very much like
trying to get people to a point of being
able to do true kind of experimental
empirical applications right I mean
that's the final section is all kind of
meant to transition into that um just
because that's primarily what I do um so
so I mean with respect to the kind of um
yeah your question here is that within
the p P scheme um you know variational
free energy is primarily used as a means
of optimizing posterior beliefs about
States right the state inference um sort
of process whereas expected free energy
is the thing where you're trying to say
okay what do I expect the kind of
rewarding of the outcomes to be and how
much information do I expect to gain you
know conditional and choosing X versus y
um so that there is a true kind of
veency thing right in the expected free
energy because you have this expected
Divergence or lack thereof between the
things you want and the things you
expect right under a policy whereas the
variational for energy is much more um a
function of it's just a function of the
observations you're getting and how you
update beliefs about the most sort of
appropriate approximate posterior over
those States right so in other words you
know if I perceive that uh you know the
observation I'm get getting is that you
know someone's like stabbing me or
something right
then the the process I go through to
minimize variational for energy that
that is what I use to infer that the
best interpretation of what's happening
to me is that I'm currently being
stacked right so so if if the idea with
variational free energy as it is at
least in in the kind of standard PDP
formalism um is a way of just getting at
the best posterior belief about the
state you're in then that state could be
something you really like or something
you really don't like right sure um so
so just when you when you see it that
way um then there is this kind of big
distinction between trying to um trying
to maximize um the consistency between
your preferred observations and the
observations you think you're going to
get um that that's just that's veency
and could relate to well-being um in a
much more direct way than just trying to
optimize your beliefs about the current
states you're in right it's interesting
that yeah you you focus more on the sort
of perceptual side of variational free
energy uh because at least the way way
that I've spoken about it and I've seen
written and I've and I've written is
that it's kind of it's kind of dual
wieldy in the sense that variational
free energy being this uh kind of upper
bound on self-information or surprisal
you can also minimize it by taking
action but then that said when we talk
about action we always frame it within
expected free energy terms so I've been
kind of thinking just again this is just
a completely sort of nent non really
fleshed out thought is that action seems
to do can
do variational free energy and expected
free energy minimization at the same
time in the sense that you know if
you're uh sort of maximization of model
evidence term the the minus log of pro
the probability of Y if you're doing
that and also you're you're maximizing
pragmatic value it seems like you're
doing both at the same time is it kind
of a an erroneous way of thinking to
alide or combine expected free energy
and variational free energy in this way
um yeah I mean like I said it's a little
bit complex because I mean um
so so okay we'll start put this um
certainly um in the uh you know what the
the accuracy of the expected free energy
calculation that you do right depends
right on whether you have good posterior
beliefs Over States um and it depends on
whether you're updating your actual
generative model appropriately based on
the patterns of observations you're
getting over time um which would
correspond to what we typically call
learning right as opposed to perception
um so obviously you're expected for
energy estimates will not be good if
your model is really bad um and so
there's an indirect dependence right on
our ability to maximize um being in the
states that we want to be in um there's
a dependence between that and using the
um and minimizing variational free
energy at least in a way that um um of
course that depends on whether you're V
minimizing variational free energy with
respect to a a model that's in fact
accurate right I mean you can get an
approximate posterior belief that
minimizes variational for energy um with
respect to a model but if your model is
very mismatched with the world then
right that approximate posterior is
still not going to be a good description
of the world and therefore you might
still end up getting observations you
really don't want when you choose
policies based on that right so right um
you know that being said I mean you know
it's a little bit you formalize it
because um the you know often when it's
kind of talked about more generically
especially in the philosophy literature
um yeah definitely variational for
energy has the kind of dual right
perception action aspect but um but
there there isn't really like a I mean
the tricky thing is is that action at
least when action is formed in the kind
of explicit planning decision- making
sense you still do require um some kind
of cost function right you still have to
have some mechanism that says I expect
action a to be better than action B sure
um and um and free energy is a function
of current observations right whereas
the the planning and decision making
kind of has to be with respect to Future
observations and that's kind of the
distinction between variational and
expected free energy um now now I say
that in addition however I mean you so
you mentioned the thing that me and
Casper had done with u you know deeply
felt affect paper
and in and there there is this kind of
further further term that can be added
into the into the active inference
formalism if you want to it doesn't
always kind of have to be there it
depends on the you know context of the
sort of task or cognitive process you
you care about um or that you're trying
to model but um where you you are
effectively comparing the expected free
energy to the variational free energy
with the new observation that you get
right and so there either will be a
match or a mismatch there
right so if it's the case for example
and under with that example if it's the
case that the um the expected for inges
gets a little mathy but but the expected
for energy Vector over over policies if
that kind of geometrically if if that
Vector points in a direction that is
consistent with um the variational for
energy of the observation that you get
right then you can kind of think of that
as being a little bit kind of like a
positive reward prediction error it's
basically saying that what you got was
um consistent with and even sort of
better than expected um compared to G so
it's kind of like f f matches with G or
is consistent with G or maybe even a
little better um nice and and that in
the in the deeply felt affect formalism
the idea was that that that uh sort of
positive prediction that positive reward
prediction ER effectively can itself be
treated as an observation that can kind
of feed into a higher level model where
it's kind of like evidence for a a
positive effective State and then that
can kind of put a prior back down on
what that what the kind of expected
value is for um the parameter associated
with that which is just this beta hyper
prior thing um and you know the function
the function of that that is interesting
right because in the in the reverse
Direction you can also have F disagree
with G right which which would just mean
that right you're expected free energy
was based on a bad model essentially
right um and so and so um you know in
that case uh you would expect that
there' be a a negative effective
response um and so that would act act
for act as evidence for this higher
level model that would say okay I'm in a
that's evidence for a negative effective
state but what that um what that beta
term ends up doing right so when you
negative affective State corresponds to
that beta value getting bigger um which
ends up being um what it what it does is
a little bit um is a little bit nuanced
as well though because if you don't
assume that there's any kind of initial
habit like prior beliefs over policies
then um effectively all the beta does is
just add noise to Choice um you could
think about it kind of like a random
exploration term in um like in like in
reinforcement learning but it's just
kind of saying like trust your expected
free energy less right there therefore
select actions a little bit more
randomly from your posterior
distribution over
policies but if you instead happen to
have precise uh habits right so you've
just the last 50 times you know you were
in this situation you chose option two
um then um and it's kind of assumed
implicitly that that must have worked
out well right if you kept doing it over
and over again then then if beta gets
big that it ends up essentially favoring
the influence of habits over um what the
expected free energy would say um so in
that case it kind of implies that uh
when you're in a negative affective
State you'll become more kind of habit
driven um and so that's that's a little
bit the way that that um the Dynamics
end up working okay excellent yeah yeah
yeah so maybe just myself and the
audience I'm going to try and do a sort
of paraphrasing slash just trying to
align what what's going up what kind of
what's going up on what's going down
yeah so I'm familiar with the gamma
parameter yeah the gamma parameter being
sort of a scale of expected free energy
estimates so it kind of tracks in a way
how confident the system is in its
action model that's the way that I think
about it beta beta is just the
hyperparameter on that it's just the
inverse of that one over beta is gamma
okay okay so that's so that's really
useful so the way I thought about is
that if you've got lower values of gamma
that means the system has lower
confidence in sort of its capacity to do
expected free energy and so it's going
to lean towards habits just so I'm aware
that means that it's
high uh beta yeah got okay so have you
seen uh this new George Dean paper that
came out the pre-print came out what
last week something like this it's a
wonderful paper it's about sort of
canalized
psychopathological behavior so very much
in line with what you're writing about
okay and exactly what they say so you
can sort of treat gamma itself as a
hidden state mhm and you can maximize
your mental act you can optimize your
mental action so as to kind of optimize
gamma in a way so it kind of looks like
okay I'm going to avoid thinking about
me certain memories or I'm going to
avoid thinking about expected you know a
a potential
future because that will lead I know
that will lead to reduced gamma a lower
estimate of my capacity to do expected
free energy I may be butchering this
um yeah I feel I feel I feel a little
limited just because I haven't read the
paper so I yeah I might not be able to
comment confidently a l sure sure sure
well I just wanted to mention it in any
case because it's a it's a nice addition
to this picture sure yeah and I mean for
on our end yeah I can all I can really
kind of say is is that yeah for for us
or at least the way that we've been we
thought about it previously is is is
that gamma gamma itself is is it is not
like sort of directly a hidden State
itself but it is like an observation
that canect as um it's it's a thing that
can be treated as an observation to
inform inference over hidden States at a
higher level nice so you have kind of
higher level that's has a posterior of
AOK and a positive effective state or
I'm in a negative effective State and
the current and the the change in gamma
after a new observation is one piece of
evidence um for changing the the
positive or negative effective State um
two things that I think they're are kind
of important there if if we're talking
about it that way again that's just one
idea but if we're talking about it that
way one is is that crucially that kind
of implies that it's not the only thing
that can act as evidence for for the
emotional state you're right so you
could have lots of other things besides
just this kind of positive or negative
prediction ER thing that that influences
right like I mean I would think that
things about your interceptive state
right like are probably important for
that um um among among other things
right so so I just I wouldn't I just
personally wouldn't want to commit
myself to saying that like it's gamma
and only gamma is directly right this
this thing um because the because in in
that formalism what ends up happening is
is just whatever your current belief is
at the higher level about your affective
State ends up putting a prior back on
what gamma is right so like so when I'm
in a negative effective State you know
going forward on the next trial or the
next time I have to make a choice that
thing is pushing gamma down right um now
I mean something something that I do
probably want to highlight though is is
is that I I doubt that that's the
complete story um for for at least a
couple of reasons one one big one is
that empirically um negative affective
States um while they are consistent
consistent with what um consistent with
what uh would be kind of suggested here
negative affective States track
something like lack of confidence in a
model that being said um typically what
that tends to look like in a lot of
other sorts of modeling Frameworks and
some empirical results is is that the
main effect that that has isn't really
to make decision- making noisier but
actually to like turn up information
seing and to turn up learning right
right right it makes sense that if I
don't think my model is very good then I
ought to kind of turn up my learning
rate so I update my beliefs faster um
you know from the next sequence of
events that I experience because I
shouldn't be trusting my model well so
it's kind of like okay I gotta hurry up
and change my model to make it accurate
again um and kind of influence of
learning rate doesn't directly fall from
anything about Gamma yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah so that's more I've been thinking
about a little bit as well in terms of
canalization that's more kind of this
negotiation between the B Matrix and the
a
matrix um
potentially might be one part of it
right if I've got particularly imprecise
uh B matricies let's say because I have
some
dopaminergic um synaptic misfiring and
so I have hyper Precision over
a then I'm going to mistrust these State
transitions more than the norm let's
say yeah I guess I guess the thing that
probably matters here is is that um
depending on the context that you're
trying to model um there's very
different things that you might need to
be there's very different parts of your
model that you might either want to be
or not wanting to be updating right
right so so so if so maybe right what
I'm not confident in is something about
my beliefs about State Transitions and
in that case I want to be effectively or
directly updating my learning rate about
the transition probabilities right I
should really pay attention to the
coincidences between State and next
state over and over again to kind of
like reoptimize that whereas if if the
thing that I'm um
not confident about is something more
about my likelihood function right more
about the mapping between states
observations um then I ought to be
changing the kind of rate at which I
changed my beliefs about that likelihood
function um now you know how you do that
itself is tricky like I said I think I
think a more kind of extended formalism
would need to be um put together if we
were going to try to turn gamma into
something that also affected
that but um but it also I don't know one
one kind of tricky thing I guess is is
that um in a lot of the kind of
practical modeling applications right
now um the way that learning is um
learning rate is adjusted is just via
kind of fixed parameter um that's
essentially just a a scaler on the um on
the updates to the um to the the counts
and the the counts that are added to the
dally distributions um for you know a or
b or you know what ever whatever one
you're happen to you happen to be
modeling learning at a given time um but
it's a little bit I mean it it's similar
to you know including these sorts of
constants um the way you do in like a
standard kind of reinforcement learning
model um but it's not quite the same as
um the way you might um do it if you
were being kind of like trying to be
fully true to basian learning um because
because in in if if you were kind of
going true Basi and learning completely
and you didn't want to have a kind of
like a hoc constant you know that just
kind of scales the updates um then it it
ought to be something that follows from
the relative precisions of the um your
prior and your um and the signal coming
from the likel right yeah um and um you
can do that um but and if you assume it
kind of constant sensory input and a
constant likelihood then you would learn
more from that um signal given that you
had flatter versus sharper prior of
states which would follow from your
transition beliefs and therefore you're
B Matrix quote unquote but um that
actually kind of when we've tried to do
that in the past it works but it's hard
to make it work without um making a
model hierarchical or at least kind of
making it kind of implicitly
hierarchical yes it's a little tricky
but it it formally the the reason for
that is is that you um in the current
schemes obser a are kind of treated as
things that are um um kind of fully like
one hot Vector like it's a you know a
wanted a bunch of zeros basically no
uncertainty about the observation where
the uncertainty comes in it's just what
state you should believe you're in given
that observation but to to get the kind
of learning that I'm talking about you
need to actually have the the the obser
to do it right in some ways you have to
actually have the observation Vector
itself have some noise
yeah yeah
yeah cross right and so that happens
naturally in a hierarchical model
because the the first level states do
have noise in them and they act as
observations for the second level I see
but but also you know for practical
applications you can just kind of
pretend your model is effectively
hierarchical by just having it be single
level but make the observations uh noisy
as opposed to being one vectors and it
does the same thing yeah well I was
thinking it the other way that um to
control these learning rates you would
need something like a metacognitive
aspect
uh yeah you could do something like that
too you could have like a higher level
like a second level state that sort of
conditional on that whatever that is it
modulates the learning rate at the level
below let me go back to this um this
George Dean paper just because again I'm
I'm quite concerned for some reason on
well not for some reason it's for good
intellectual honesty that I don't
misspeak and I don't uh you know
so and I'm sort of curious again about
what you think so I've just got it up
here they say
um yeah so in effective inference the
system not only possesses an estimate of
action model confidence described as
implicitly metacognitive but another
layer of the generative model can be
added so that the confidence estimate
itself becomes a hidden state that the
system infers using the same mechanics
of perceptual
inference so that's kind of similar to
in a sense what I was saying right the
the gammer itself is becoming the hidden
state but I think what the point that
they're making there is that you're not
just doing perceptual updating you're
also doing uh planning as
inference so you can do in terms of
mental action attentional schemes you
can deploy certain mental actions such
that the observations you make are going
to be either you know increasing the
likelihood of being in that hidden state
or not and that's what you know that's
whe whether that's thinking about
something that's bad that's going to
happen in the future or something bad
that happened in the past you're more
likely to avoid thinking those things
because you're aware that
probabilistically you might end up in
low gamma yeah that's interesting I
guess there's a few different things
here where I'm just I don't know I mean
my initial go-to and we start talking
about all of this is kind of like how I
would like you know write it down you
know yeah yeah yeah make it kind of you
know work formally and so there's kind
of like a few different things that kind
of mixed together in there um so I mean
like one one thing I could totally see
which I thought was what you were
talking about a second ago was was like
um instead of the gamma based kind of
hierarchical updating thing that we were
talking about before like that kind of
second level State part of its
likelihood back down to the first level
could also be something about like the
the learning rate right so it could
directly through this kind of additional
Connection in the second level
likelihood you know when I'm in a
negative effective State turn up the
turn up the learning right at the lower
level um which isn't so like so much
intentional or kind of like
controlled right it's just something
that kind of like happens automatically
as a function of whatever you infer your
effective state is um that's a little
different I suppose from if you built in
a policy
itself that controlled something like
the like transitions to like attentional
States yes so we've done that we've done
that some more like emotion inference
models right where you can kind of you
could kind of selectively choose okay
now I'm going to pay attention to my
current veilance all right now I'm going
to pay attention to my arousal level um
where you can kind of use a second
hidden State factor to kind of like pull
out slices of the likelihood tensor that
that encode the Precision of the
observations um um with respect to the
mapping to a different hidden State
Factor um but uh but so there's there's
that kind of thing you don't actually
need explicit hierarchy for that you
just going to need separate orthogonal
State factors like in practice but um
but yeah so you could do that and then
the third thing I guess it makes me
think of is is something that I I played
around with a little bit that I think is
actually a really cool idea but haven't
done anything really with is that um you
can try to account for like what can
still be like a kind of like basy in
form of like motivated cognition that
would look kind of biased from the
outside by um you know because if in a
second level model you're um you're
treating the first level States as
observations for the second level then
that means like you can have a prior
preference distribution over yes first
level States right so then effectively
like you actually just like want to
believe some things and not others right
you you want to believe some things and
not others then like the optimal policy
um will could be something that looks
super anti-asian from a fully like
epistemic perspective sure but probably
is optimal under the actual scheme that
you've got in place yeah yeah yeah
exactly right but but externally right
yes I mean this is exactly the point
they're coming to they they speak of
sort of avoidant mental action or
motivated in attention right um and this
idea is that you're kind of Performing
the second order inference over the
model precision as I said but you have
this kind of predictive model with model
precision as the hidden State such that
I mean the way they talk about is how
will I feel if I do that but with
respect to mental action sure which I
think I think it's very I don't know I
just thought it was very cool and very
much up your yeah absolutely I mean yeah
when it comes to the affective stuff I
totally agree like I said I'm super
interested in this I mean it uh I mean
in part of makes me like like I both
think it's really cool and it also makes
me slightly like empirically
uncomfortable and the reason for that is
is that like I'm pretty sure it makes
like like actually testing like whether
a model like this is kind of like the
the best model of human behavior
basically I think it makes it kind of UN
fiable right right right right well it
can account for basically anything but
let's jump into that then I mean you
when we actually spoke on email you were
Keen to sort of mention that you're not
just doing pure simulation work and
you're doing empir what you call well I
think what is called empirical
computational Psychiatry whereby you fit
models to behavioral data in clinical
populations which is super cool but I'm
not a mathematician
so and I assume a lot of the audience
aren mathematicians either so perhaps
you could just in sort of a broad brush
approach describe the distinction
between uh pure simulation work and
empirical computational
Psychiatry yeah I mean I guess I think
the the cool part about doing simulation
stuff is is that you're like pretty
under constrained right like like
there's a there's a kind of like
creativity about it and you can kind of
get really complicated and you know it
allows you to kind of simulate some cool
mechanisms um but a lot of times like
the the concern I suppose is that they
become a lot of like Just So Stories in
a sense right like because you know I
could come up with probably like 10
different generative models that would
uh you know that would hypothesize
somewhat different mechanisms um but
they would produce all the kind of like
behavioral signatures of the sort of
thing we're trying to explain right
right so so I think it's important
important to be able to find ways to
actually you know test you know which of
these models are actually good you know
like accurate descriptions of what's
actually going on in the brain um and um
and so you know for that right you need
to get these models to have direct
contact with data somehow um and um and
so usually you know so the sort of thing
that you know we will do and and what I
should say another thing is is that um
you know like how good a model fit
data um is always a relative comparison
right I mean you can't there are
absolute metrics of model fit but
usually you want to kind of say okay
here's a space of possible generative
models um you know that that hypothesize
different sorts of algorithms that are
being used or or or different just model
structures but that assume you know
underlying the same underlying algorithm
um and then you kind of want and you
want to do like basian model comparison
right just say out of all these models
which model does the data provide the
most evidence for um and you know like
that that actually allows you to be able
to test whether or not like an active
inference model um or what an active
inference model would a given active
inference model would predict um you
know actually reproduces behavior that
people actually do right right um and um
so so I just don't yeah I mean to be to
be scientific about it I just wouldn't
want or I think I think it's important
that for people to take for for people
outside of just the kind of like active
inference Community proper right to
actually kind of take these things
seriously and think that they're moving
um moving science forward um that uh you
know we need to be able to actually show
that these things are improving right
how well we can predict um what brain
and behavior actually look like compared
to lots of other simpler models that
have been around for you know much
longer than active inference right so so
um I mean you know comp computational
Psychiatry is a fairly um you it's
fairly new field but you know there's a
lot of there's more and more people
working in it but most of them are not
um coming from like an active inference
background you know they more tend to
focus on simpler reinforcement learning
models um that um you know at the end of
the day don't tend to be really too
different in what they predict from from
active inference in a lot of cases um so
it you know the trick is kind of you
know finding the right kinds of
decision-making or Behavioral or
perceptual tasks to have people to have
you know participants come in and do
whether they be healthy or whether they
be patient groups um to try to um you
know to see in other words you have to
find tasks where it's clear that a
particular active inference model would
actually make different
predictions than a simpler um
reinforcement learning model and um you
know we've started to do quite a bit
more of that I am you know there's a you
know for anyone for anyone who wants to
come a little plug
uh the um one of my uh current grad
students um is uh presenting um well she
just about to submit for a talk or a
poster um for the computational
Psychiatry conference um this summer in
Minneapolis in July um and it's uh and
this has been kind of our most thorough
attempt at this um lately is we just
have a a fairly simple like explore
exploit um sort of like three arm banded
task that involves trade-offs between
information seeking and reward seeking
and so it does kind of match right where
where active inference is supposed to
kind of show show its strengths with the
directed exploration um in this case
primarily with respect to the uh novelty
term right so this would be like
parameter exploration not State
exploration um but um but so more or
less we identified I think like this is
like table essentially of um something
like 30 different possible RL models and
like 30 different equ like equivalent
complexity active inference model
something like is a really massive model
space um and you know fit all these
models to um to the um to behavioral
data and a couple hundred people um and
both a both a Taiwanese sample actually
and an American sample um and um and
just done model comparison across these
um and um and the the models that tend
to win are more complicated models um
there's a the the two the two kind of
best models in what we found so far one
is
one is an active inference model that
assumes um that people have um one
forgetting rate um and two separate
learning rates for wins and losses um
separately so basically update your
beliefs more or less when you get a win
versus when you get a loss um and then a
kind of like Dynamic decision noise um
sort of term that um is based on the the
beta thing actually based on the based
on the um updates of the uh the beta
gamma um term that we were talking about
where where effectively what that ends
up meaning is that um when
people get an outcome that's unexpected
right then gamma goes down and so the
posterior polies flattens out and so
essentially their choices become more
exploratory in the in the randomness
sense um when they get outcomes that
they weren't expecting right if they
were negative if they get outcomes that
are better than expected and it's
positive then they become sort of more
deterministic in going with with what
the model would say is the best choice
um and so that's the best like active
inference model that tends to fit so
it's very complex it has like five or
six parameters something like that um
and the the winning RL model is slightly
different it assumes Dynamic learning as
opposed to Dynamic forgetting or I mean
as opposed to Dynamic decision noise um
but the the point is that the main the
main difference between these models
ends up not really so much being
differences in exploratory Behavior so
much as whether or not they include um
basian forms of learning um right right
the main thing that the main thing that
active inference does that's really
different when you match it to kind of
an equivalent complexity RL model is um
is that active inference models are kind
of with the with the derish
distributions again the details of that
don't matter for non-mathematical people
it just basically means that in an RL
model you're just kind of updating your
beliefs about the expected um reward
probabilities whereas an active
inference you're keeping track of those
reward probabilities but also you're
keeping track of your confidence in
those beliefs about the reward probab
abilities um and um and so that's what
um the the kind of take-home with it for
for what for what she's done is um
mainly that the um the ability for the
two models to um predict behavior is
actually the best two models um is
actually fairly similar but basian model
comparison does um select the active
inference model over the over the uh RL
model um and because the differences in
accuracy between the models aren't uh
aren't amazingly different um ends up
relating probably a little bit more to
like complexity cost differences um and
you know kind of evaluation of the
independent like how independent each
parameter is and explaining the behavior
things like that um so so anyway I mean
so a lot of what we've been doing is
kind of attempting to say okay well you
know how much better you know does
active inference actually do right in
explaining in explaining behavor
behavior is it the kind of most
parsimonious accurate explanation for um
how people actually do make decisions in
information seeking contexts um so
that's a little bit you know where you
know kind of the approach that we take
so that and then using those things um
by also having people in patient groups
with like depression or anxiety or
substance use disorders um do these same
sorts of tasks and then see whether um
you know we can explain clinically
relevant differences in these you know
between patients and healthy comparisons
um through differences in the actual
parameter estimates right so maybe it's
the case that so one thing that we have
found right is is that pretty
consistently substance users in active
inference models tends to show um much
slower learning rates from negative
outcomes um than positive outcomes so
they kind of it takes a lot more times
of them choosing a suboptimal thing
before they kind of change what they do
um I found that I found that an
interesting result uh your 2023 paper
elevated decision on certainty and
reduced avoidance drives in depression
anxiety and substance use disorders I
may that's a different one but yeah this
might be slightly different but I found
maybe maybe I misinterpreted what you
said there but this idea that um
individuals at least with substance used
to S Show A reduced sensitivity to
unpleasant
stimuli yeah okay so so it's yeah so
there's a yeah so that's a that's a with
a different task um it's actually the
same the same sample but it's a
different task I guess the prior one is
learning rates right the first one yeah
so it kind of depends right the learning
rate one again that's with like a bandit
task and so it's it is about kind of EXP
expl exploit updating beliefs about
reward probabilities Etc whereas the
approach avoidance conflict task is a
little different it's not a learning
task it's purely just kind of a planning
forward-looking task yeah yeah and in
that one it's more or less there's a
different kind of number of you know
points that you know people can win but
they have to also choose to go through
some pretty unpleasant aect seeing some
pretty seeing and hearing some pretty
unpleasant effective stimul at the same
time so you going to have to plan
whether okay do I prefer to kind of move
toward the side of this Runway that
means the probability is higher I'll
kind of get this safe neutral outcome
but no points or whether I'll whether I
expect it to be kind of worth it to me
right to like under a certain point
value try to act in a way that will
increase the probability that I'll get
the points but also see the super
unpleasant stuff right and and in that
case there's um you know this is sort of
task that's been used in
non-computational modeling ways several
times in the past but the the main kind
of metric if you don't do it the
computational way is more or less just
this General kind of unidimensional
approach avoidance thing whereas the the
modeling version is a little bit more
helpful because we can estimate the beta
parameter for these people and then we
can also estimate um certain things
about the shape of their preference
distribution um and um and what that
shows so we can kind of use that to
dissociate two different aspects of
approach avoidance conflict one is this
kind of like uncertainty about decisions
and the other is this actual kind of you
know approach avoidance drive right um
and the yeah the results for that are
actually kind of surprising you know
because like in the in the depression
anxiety and in the substance users um
they tend to show um greater the
patients tend to show greater decision
uncertainty so they have higher beta
values but they um they actually show um
more precise preferences for the for the
points which basically me that they're
means that they're kind of more willing
to go through the negative AFF stuff I
was very surprised by that yeah so
they're actually less avoidant right so
they're more uncertain but they're less
avoidant and that's we've now shown that
in four studies you know so it's a very
consistent result across multiple
samples I read that and I had to read it
twice uh because I was really like I
really expected the other way around
because we're used to hearing that
avoidance is the kind of number one
driver of a psychological disorder like
generalized anxiety disorder or so what
what do you imagine is going on here I
mean I think one just talking in terms
of very lame and non computational terms
yeah there's there's the overexposure of
people with psychological disorders to
negative stimuli in the first place so
what's negative for a healthy control is
well it's all relative right and if
you've been exposed to overtly negative
things like your own emotions over and
over again maybe you have a reduced
sensitivity yeah I mean there's you know
I mean we don't we don't really have
like unfortunately I mean our our
hypothesis going in was absolutely what
you said originally right that we would
get more avoidance in the patient groups
um but uh you know we were just hoping
that the the modeling would help us kind
of distinguish these couple different
kind of Dimensions right of of of
approach voidance conflict um but uh but
definitely we didn't expect the the more
approach stuff in the in the in the
patient groups um that being said yeah
so we so because of that we don't have
kind of a bunch of other we don't have
all the measures that we probably would
have gotten um to try to dissociate
different possible explanations for that
kind of unexpected avoidance uh or
unexpected lack of avoidance um so it it
becomes a little speculative but um one
thing is absolutely I mean that's one
thing you might you might suspect is
what you said that um you know if if
people uh if people just in general are
in this kind of heightened negative
affective State then you know you might
expect that makes them more sensitive to
other negative affective things but you
also might make that also might think
they're a little bit habituated to it
yes exactly what would that look like in
terms of a kind of PM DP scheme because
I guess we associate habits with
action with the priv value over or priv
beliefs over action when we're talking
about
habituated uh responses to stimuli I
mean I guess it is it's in a sense
action but what what shape does that
take um yeah I mean so so like I said in
in the official model that we were
fitting it doesn't really include any
include a the Dynamics of habituation
we're just kind of estimating the what
the shape of their preference
distribution is right to explain their
behavior um and so it so then the
explanation just ends up being that they
have a more precise preference for for
winning the points or or or less the the
the the magnitude of the the probability
of the negative outcomes in the
preference distribution which again
doesn't really mean probability it just
means they they dis prefer the negative
stuff less right um is uh is um you know
that ends up explaining it but but um
but what would it look like if you
included some sort of actual learning
dynamic
for um for
habituation um I mean so this kind of
habituation is is really not so much
more about habitual action as it is just
the level of sensitivity you have to
stimulate right so yes so it's a little
more has this flavor of okay if I see
something over and over again then my
response to it each time is less right
so right so um I think you could cost
that in terms of action
um it
it well I mean it's okay so I'm thinking
in terms of traditional therapeutic
responses right like in terms of
exposure response prevention therapy for
example you would you at least have an
element of it which said that a uh
dysfunctional avoidance response again
this is a non-active inference way of
framing it but just in a Layman sense it
entrenches the the the severity or the
perception of the severity of the
stimulus yeah so I mean we have you know
I mean I wouldn't necessarily have
expected you seen it but happen to I
mean we do have this paper we published
a couple years ago as a simulation paper
specifically on mechanisms of uh
possible mechanisms of CBT in in a pal
DP so we actually did simulate exposure
therapy in particular nice um and um but
it was The crucial kind of thing we were
looking for there was whether or not we
could kind of capture um make
predictions about the ways that
cognitive interventions like reappraisal
would interact with behavioral
interventions like exposure therapy um
and um and I mean some of some of some
of that we ended up being kind of kind
of excited about it seemed consistent
with results or with you know when I
talk to clinicians because I work with a
lot of clinicians um you know what they
say but where where with that I mean the
the kind of you know habituation was
much more about like
so if a person has a strong if a person
has a strong expectation that like if
they choose a certain action then the
things they are going to observe are
things that they really don't like right
so things that have a very low uh
preference level um then you know it
follows all us being equal they're not
going to they're going to take actions
that don't lead them to those to make
those observations right but the problem
is is that when those when those um when
those uh uh beliefs about the expected
outcomes of actions are are wrong right
then if they just avoid it every time
right then they can they can never
update their beliefs right so I mean
exposure is essentially kind of this
kind of like uh clinician facilitated
directed exploration right right right
you know they kind of push you to go
take this action right that's gonna make
you see okay what actually happens when
I'm in this state that I've been
avoiding um and so and so the kind of
habituation in that sess just ends up
being once they start actually seeing
What observations they really get when
they're avoiding then they just you know
it just updates their likelihood
function right
under that state um but um but the the
interesting thing at least in in that
paper was a lot more of how that
interacts with um your um cognitive
beliefs so because because you can also
and this is often what happens right is
is that when when people go through
exposure therapy um they will they can
um even after those respon the negative
responses kind of go away and they start
to say okay now no I believe like in the
context of spider phobia for example
like no okay actually you know I believe
this spider is safe now right and so
their responses their affective
responses like died down but you know
you bring them back in a couple days
later they see the spider and they have
the negative responses again sure right
so it doesn't kind of like stick around
it doesn't generalize um you know and so
why is that right because under a simple
under a simple kind of like unlearning
story um they would have just
overwritten their old likelihood
function right so they shouldn't right
their generative models just be
different they shouldn't have those
responses again um you know so what
explains that well what explains that
has to be that they um that they don't
take evidence they don't take the
evidence from The Unexpected outcomes
when they see a spider um as evidence
that their likelihood function was wrong
they take it instead as evidence that
they've actually transitioned into a new
hidden hidden State
context so that now so now they believe
okay I am in the safe context and then
they just update their likelihood under
the safe context Ah that's interesting
right so then all you have to do is say
okay well if there's any uncertainty in
the transition function then even though
they believe they're in the safe context
now to come back in a couple days later
there's more uncertainty over what
context they're in so the responses come
back because the likelihood function
under the danger context still says
right bad things will happen if spider
so how would you resolve that um yeah so
so it um I mean so one thing you want to
do then is you want to you want to try
your best as a as a therapist in some
way to um to not use cognitive
approaches to try to like make people
believe oh actually this is really you
know this is really safe right yeah
you're gonna go in this room you're
gonna see this spider yeah but it is
safe right right like you have to have
them actually maintain some kind of
uncertainty about what context there in
in right because only in that case if
there's like a like in the simulations
more or less like we showed is like if
you keep the posterior distribution that
they have about the context there and if
you kind of keep that impr precise right
if you maintain the kind of cognitive
uncertainty then when they get the
unexpected observations that bad things
don't happen then it does overwrite the
likelihood under both States right um
under both hidden both hidden contexts
and then it does generalize right um and
that's um that's actually uh consistent
with this kind of cool study that um Sam
gersman um has written some stuff about
um back in like 2015 is it's like been a
little while but but where you can do
more or less the same thing with rats um
with like just classical conditioning
experiments where you know this is kind
of you know you play a tone they get
shocked you know like over and over
again with some probability so now you
play the tone and they kind of jump or
freeze or do something implying that
they'll shock um and then the standard
thing to do during Extinction is you
just present the tone over and over
again you don't show the shock at all or
you don't give shock at all and so then
their responses slowly die um but
similar to with exposure therapy you
bring the rats back a day later you play
the tone again and they do have this
kind of spontaneous recovery is what
it's called where they start to have the
fear response again um which means
they're doing basically the same thing
right the rats too are just inferring
okay I'm not sure if I'm still in the
safe context um so so what they showed
though is that if you do the extinction
um if you do the
extinction time course a little
differently um then you can actually
prevent this spontaneous recovery um and
the way they did it is instead of during
Extinction just abruptly completely
stopping the the association between the
tone and the shock what they did is they
just said okay for a little while tone
is assoc associated with shock 90% of
the time okay now for a while tone is
associated with shock 80% of the time
okay now 70% of the time they tape of
them off yeah so and what that does you
can kind of think about it is the
prediction errors are never that big
right and if the prediction erors are
never that big then that's not good
evidence for the shift in context right
right so does cause this slow
overwriting right of the original
likelihood function as opposed to
promoting the state inference thing and
when they did it that way and then they
tested their routes later they didn't
have the spontaneous recovery like the
the fear responses didn't come back
um and that is fascinating it's very
it's it's quite counterintuitive
though yeah I think you would one would
be under the presumption that if you
just kept
providing
evidence you know if you kept tying an
observation to a different
state that would just become entrenched
but it it does make sense that that
itself becomes this kind of crystallized
thing and then once you take them out
and put them back in then the previous
one still has that Precision that's
that's that's really fascinating you
also said something very interesting
there which was um it was kind of under
the radar but the difference
between having a strong preference to be
somewhere or to have something or to be
something or whatever
versus uh H like having a strong
dispreference not to be somewhere be
something have something so a positive
versus a double negative
M I've often found this in in active
inference that I don't think it's been
particularly well codified what the
difference is between those so people
say oh um I want to be um 37.8 right in
some subpersonal way I want to be 37.8
degrees Celsius and so I take action to
restore that but you could well cast as
I don't want to be 40 degrees
celsius yeah right is there a is there a
technical difference between those
um so I mean one one thing that I guess
is a is kind of unique about the way
that active inference en codes
preferences compared to you know more
kind of like traditional formalisms like
reinforcement learning that cast things
explicitly in terms of reward function
um is that you know strictly speaking an
active inference agent isn't really
trying to maximize reward they're trying
to minimize Divergence from a target
distribution right and that actually has
certain interesting implications um but
one one uh
one thing to consider with that though
is that is that um unlike in things like
reinforcement learning um all of your
preferences kind of constrain each other
in the sense that the whole distribution
has to add up to
one right um so so uh you can um so I
think that you will have to kind of
relatively
speaking
um basically you will only be able to
specify relative preferences um so so I
think that so I think that if you if you
have a distrib preference distribution
where the kind of highest mass is over
you know like 38 is degrees right then
then the fact that it kind of tails off
on both sides simultaneously guarantees
that you dis prefer being above or below
that um so so I don't know explicitly
whether or not there is um whether or
not there's there's any way to um encode
those in a way that's different um there
are interesting things you can do by
putting kind of like negative
preferences for something and positive
preferences for another thing if there's
like an observation you can lock as kind
of like the Baseline value of like zero
um when the thing gets
normalized um to turn it back into an
actual probability distribution then
then it does still end up being kind of
a precise
uh preference for one thing and dis
preference for the other and they do
still end up being relative to each
other though so um and the main the main
thing that we tend to see when we do
like simulation stuff and those sorts of
settings is it just tends to um lead to
this kind of like anti- exloration
behavior um when when you know one
thing's really negative where it's kind
of like the uh the uh agent is just kind
of this like you know better safe than
sorry you know sort of
conservative behavior um but I um but I
think there are there should definitely
be ways of encoding those in terms of
all just kind of relative relative
positive values that end up normalizing
to the same distribution cool yeah I I
think part of the reason why I asked
that is because I think it's a point
that you making uh the papers that
you've written on interceptive inference
which is that when uh we speak of sort
of So-Cal aberant inter receptive
inference a lot of papers are not very
clear whether they're talking talking
about the underweighting of Prior or the
overweighting of the likelihood
distribution sure um I think part of the
problem is people think of uh Precision
waiting as like a necessary Zero Sum
game such that you can't have both so if
I have uh reduced Precision over my
likelihood by necessity that will lead
to increased Precision over my prior if
I decreased Precision of my prior by
necessity that leads to an uptake in the
Precision of the likelihood but what you
show at least in this 2020 paper the one
that I read from plus um where you did
the interceptive perturbation condition
is that this isn't the
case so where where do you think that
kind of false intuition comes from that
oh well it comes it comes from it comes
from the fact that people usually in the
way that they at least in these more
kind of conceptual papers um comes in
part from the fact that uh these are
Under um uh they're talking about models
that have gaan assumptions with
continuous distribution
um because if you have if you just have
along a single Dimension right if you
have like a distribution that defines
the likelihood function and a
distribution that defines the um prior
belief then then there are right when I
turn up one or turn down the other then
there's a bunch of different ways that I
can kind of combine those things to lead
to the same posterior um so it does
become hard to distinguish um so it
depends on the dimensionality and
depends on whether you're were talking
about continuous or categorical
distributions
um so so in in the in the case of what
we're doing these are discrete
distributions right so in discrete
models with the dimensionality the way
that we have it set up um it makes uh it
makes clearly distinct behavioral
predictions but um but in the uh in the
kind of unidimensional gaussian um setup
um then you you do get this more um only
the relative waiting matters yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah that makes sense okay so
thus far I I know we we haven't got too
much time but thus far I know we've kind
of been speaking generally
about perceptual updating and parameter
updating um or parameter learning and
belief updating but we also have
structure learning and active inference
and I think you make a really nice point
to say that sort of something like
introducing a concept to distinguish
between um or or to yes to let's say
split up a concept that you have before
so if I had anger now maybe I can turn
that into rage and fury sure um I think
I believe you call that emotional
granularity yeah in the in the yeah in
the emotion in the emotional state
inference context yeah we would talk
about that in terms of granularity or
yeah that's usually the probably the
best way to talk about it yeah it's a
really fascinating concept because it it
it I think on on first glance it seems
like a it seems like a sort of just
linear benefit the more emotional gr
granularity I have the better um yeah I
mean what the what the direct
relationship would be between like the
uh the number of you know States in a
state space and uh and something to do
with gamma I think is is going to be
fairly indirect um but for a number of
reasons but um I mean I think with most
things right I mean the general answer
is going to be that um it's not so much
about complexity per se as more
complexity than necessary yeah right so
so um right you you know complexity
adding complexity is good if it
increases accuracy right so so um so
what it would mean right to be more
complex than necessary would be that
there's a mismatch to the actual
generative
process so I think that I think that the
um if you have more right if you're
overfitting right to the to the
generative process right if you if
you're inventing more categories than
there actually are distinctions to make
um then obviously it's going to be
problematic right because you're you're
going to think you have more information
than actually you do um but but so long
as but so long as you're carving up your
state space in a more fine grained way
and that actually does add to the
informativeness of the information that
your generative model uh is able to kind
of pick up and then use to inform policy
selection then then I would expect it
would be the more the better right it's
just the more so it's the the more accur
information you have the more informed
policy selection will be right so so as
long as as long as you have you're good
at inferring the right you know
posterior over what emotional state
you're in and each emotional state that
you kind of have have acquired into your
generative model um if if each of those
does in fact make unique um um
predictions about patterns of current
and future observations under that state
then then yeah I mean it'll be better
just because it'll should right on
average just make policy selection more
informed right right right but um yeah
thinking more broadly about the
distinction between structure learning
and parameter learning do you see these
as bright dividing
lines or do you see them as being kind
of philosophically vague as to when
parameter learning becomes structure
learning um you know like I guess it's
just it's just tricky I mean like you
get into the weeds with some of this
stuff because so you do that's what
we're here
people use structural learning the term
structural learning to mean several
different things right so I mean
structural learning itself is is a kind
of like superordinate category with a
bunch of different kind of Exemplar
things within it um so you know I mean
we did I don't know if you saw this this
just one paper on structureal learning
specifically that you know we put out a
few years ago where it was kind of like
you know people that you know there was
just like kind of a dumb example of uh
people trying to like learn like coar
grain or fine grain different types of
like birds and fish and stuff why right
yeah and and you know so that it was
like you could just learn like these
broad categories of Bird and Fish Or you
could kind of like learn to carve it up
into specific types of birds specific
types of fish and they just kind of each
of those was defined with with respect
to specific like patterns of covariance
among certain sorts of observable
features right like wings versus gills
and size and color and things like that
but um you know and in that particular
case the way that like structure
learning was post was in relation to
kind of like
inferring how many states need to be in
your state space right to account for
account for data um and so and so um
that has to do with kind of the setup of
the structure of the generative model
proper right like how many how many
types of States how many states how many
how many how many state factors how many
levels of States within each state
Factor Etc um you know so in the in the
general pomdp scheme that is distinguish
able from parameter learning in the
sense that parameters are usually kind
of um the the values of the entries into
the matrices within you know things like
the likelihood function transition
function Etc um that you update but you
update those under the assumption that
like you know number of number of
columns in the in each Matrix are are
kind of fixed right right right so so so
if you're talking about kind of this
granularity kind of fine graining of of
your of the Concepts that you have um
then then there is a clear distinction
between um between uh those examples of
parameter learning and structure
learning but um like I said there's
other types of structureal learning and
the actual
implementation of how you do structural
learning also matters because you know
in our example um you know we we use
this kind of like little trick right
where we just kind of said you know
we're we're actually gonna you know
stick the matrices in as though there's
a bunch of these kind of extra unused
columns you know so we didn't have to
kind of like explicitly add states to
the state space we just kind of had a
bunch of states that were just kind of
like sitting there silently unused yeah
and then the way that and then the way
that the thing kind of worked was just
that you know what they meant to be
unused was the distributions were just
completely flat right so they didn't
predict really anything unique about the
observations and so and so the way that
that would work is just that um
more or less that if you got some
pattern of observations that was
consistent with one of the kind of
informative likelihood functions under a
kind of state that you already had um
then the posterior would be precise over
that state and you know you would have a
basically zero posterior over all the
unused columns and so you wouldn't have
any parameter updating under those
columns but um but if you had some
pattern of observations and they were
really inconsistent with any of the
informative mappings that you had then
effectively what that would do is it
would mean that the flat mappings would
would better explain the data right
right right right and you know and as
soon as like the flat mapping better
explains the data then you end up with a
precise posterior over one of these
unused columns right whichever one
happens to explain it best and then you
just start learning the parameters under
that new column right so so and then you
that's just a way of learning a new
informative mapping so it's kind of like
effectively now you have a new column
you've expanded your state space right
yeah and you could you could do that a
little bit more explicitly than we did
by writing in some additional function
that like explicitly you know just like
added new columns to the state space or
something as opposed to just having
these unused ones sitting
around but my point is is that the the
relationship between structure learning
and parameter learning is very they're
very tightly intertwined in in that case
right because like when you start
learning the parameters like that the
thing that leads you to start learning
parameters is the the exact thing that
is causing you to do structure learning
why why why why right yes exactly so
again one that's one implementation
right so I'm saying that that won't be
true that doesn't need to be true um
generically but that will be true in
some
cases yeah yeah yeah yeah well and it
seems like they
all to yeah they all lean on one another
in some kind of recursive manner where
you can't really have structure Learning
Without learning the parameters in you
know of that structure in the first
place nor the belief updating that
allows you to kind of get there in the
first place right in a dynamic system in
a dynamically changing system yeah I
mean I think I think it's just and again
I can't I can't really say with
confidence how well this will generalize
to other cases of structure learning or
or even just other kind of generative
model setups and things like that but
but yeah at least in this case it's kind
of you you have to you have to
effectively infer that that the current
informative parameters in parameter
based mappings that you have are not
doing a good job of explaining something
and then end up with a very low
posterior distribution um over or a
posterior that assigns a very low
probability to any of the States you
currently have in your state space and
then yeah and then so it's like you get
the right posterior based on you know
that based on the fact that your current
parameters are not good expl you know
don't provide good explanations for the
data and then by starting to update
different set of parameters you end up
leading to doing something that is
effectively structural learning so it's
yeah they're just very yeah it is all
just very kind of tightly connected yeah
yeah yeah well it'd be interesting to
see if you could sort of disambiguate
them you know in a model like whether
you could just
have I guess do yeah conceptually though
I think that's tricky right because you
somehow have to say I need structural
learning only because well exactly
that's why I meant kind of bu this
recursive nature I mean I don't know if
recursion is even the right way of
talking about it it might be sort of
nesting um in some sense that belief
updating drives paramet updating which
like ultimately feeds into structure
learning yeah yeah cool so final
question big question you got this paper
coming out the empir the so-called
empirical status of predictive
coding H and active inference but yeah
and active inference I yes is that the
is that the whole name of the paper yeah
um it's a sort of classic critique
leverage that active inference that it's
self-contained and it's an echo chamber
and it's a lot of philosophers and
mathematicians kind of spitballing these
fancy ideas but it doesn't this is a
common critique I'm not saying it's true
oh okay yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah oh well
it would be it would be odd if it if I
would to formulate that position as the
host of this podcast oh no no no sorry I
thought I thought you were saying that
that was the the thrust of our paper no
no no no no I'm saying it's a common
critique from those on the outside I
don't remember saying all of that no no
no no I I know you didn't but it's a
common critique at least I mean that
might be uh oversimplifying the critique
but that you know this Theory of
Everything um is overgeneralizing and it
doesn't have evidential an evidential
basis where having done this all of Deep
dive into the empirical status of active
inference and predictive coding what are
the conclusions that you guys have
drawn um I mean I I just think I kind of
think at the end of the day I mean it
mounts to be something kind of similar
to what I think you'll see in a lot of
review papers for most things right is
this is just that there's a lot of stuff
where more work needs to be done sure to
be for it to be definitive I mean that's
kind of like the the very oversimplified
conclusion I mean I would say that I I
mean one thing that that I hope that we
tried to make clear um um is just it's
more that like there's just lots of
different levels of claims with respect
to both predictive coding and active
inference and they all kind of need to
be tested in a way that's a little bit
at least partially independent of each
other right so I mean especially in the
philosophy literature people will even
talk about really broad like categories
like you know just like predictive
processing you know quote unquote but
like I mean if you want to move from
that down to stuff that is actually
testable um
requires a bunch of there's a bunch of
kind of layers that you have to kind of
work through to get there right so you
can have to say Okay well predictive
processing it's very generic idea that
in some way one of the main things the
brain does is predict stuff I guess
right it's like okay well you know two
of the most kind of like prominent but
certainly not the only possible
categories for that are like predictive
coding and perception and active
inference and action but then even from
there right I mean like predictive
coding makes particular um explan or
makes particular predictions if what
you're talking about is um something
about the uh the the the the predictive
coding algorithm right as defined right
which is which doesn't necessarily need
to make predictions at the level of the
kind of like neur neurobiological
implementation right so and same thing
same thing with active inference right
active inference for say okay well what
type of active inference are we talking
about are we talking about like the you
know continuous State spaces are we
talking about discreet State spaces and
you know like are we talking about um
you know commitments related to you know
some of these like claims about you know
the gamma stuff and dopamine or you know
are we just talking about things about
categorical State inference and that and
that that depends on minimizing
variational free energy um through like
a variational message passing scheme
right and okay are we actually
hypothesizing variational message
passing are we hypothesizing marginal
message passing or are we hypothesizing
that the implementation draws or that
the algorithm is doing some sort of like
belief propagation thing right and and
then even there right that's still all
just at the algorithmic level then you
have to say Okay well if I commit to
some algorithm right if I commit to PDP
discret State space you know this
particular generative model structure
for this task um you know with this you
know with this message passing scheme
you know as I said then all right
there's like probably at least like 20
ways that you could set up a neural
network right to solve that right so
then you also have to have a hypothesis
about okay what am I what what
implementation you know am I am I
testing right and what are the
predictions of that implementation right
so if I'm doing something at the
Neuroscience level then I'm G say okay
it's kind of this very kind of
hierarchical thing where it's like you
know this particular neural prediction
that falls from this imple hypothesis
and implementation that falls from this
specific narrow algorithmic commitment
you know like from this larger kind of
framework you know what I'm saying so
it's like you start making exclusions
yeah so testing so testing these things
is what it even means to be testing
these things is is is kind of
complicated because um by the time you
can actually get down to something
that's empirically testable um you've
narrowed it down a ton right and ruling
out one implementation doesn't falsify
yeah itive processing nor does it
falsify active inference right it just
means you ruled out that a particular
implementation of a particular algorithm
you know within the active inference
framework Etc so it's like okay well now
on testing like implementation
hypothesis too so it's a you know so
that that's tough right so then um but a
lot of you know but a lot of what's been
done is much more um well I should say
with with predictive coding a lot of
stuff's been done at the at the neural
level with active inference it's very
minimal has been done done in terms like
Neuroscience um neuro neuroscientific
studies like Philip shorton be had a
cool study in like 2015 where they did
um where they did uh some of the um some
of the uh like midbrain dopamine um
results in relation to um some of the uh
the beta updating stuff I mean it's
called Alpha in that paper so like
slightly older fism but but same basic
idea um but so you know so there's that
and then you know there's kind of like
with predictive coding for example um
you know I think I think many people
would say that one you know one specific
commitment at least to kind of like
vanilla um forms of you know hypothesis
predictive coding architectures is like
okay well prediction errors get passed
upward predictions get passed downward
you know there's kind of these separate
populations of prediction units and
prediction error units yeah typically
it's like okay well the prediction eror
units are in like cortical R 23 and you
know like and the Deep you know
prediction units are in you know
parameter cells in layer five five and
six um you know but then you know when
you actually look at like some of these
more complicated like canonical
microcircuit models and things like that
that that really explore in detail right
how you would do predictive coding um in
a way that would kind of match up to the
actual like cortical columnar
architectures that we know about you
know from like micro anatomical you know
actual brain studies like you know I
mean it becomes way more complicated
right you have like specific roles of
like granular cells and then you have
kind of like the sorts of predictions
and prediction that are hypothesized to
be like passed around through like
different inter neurons and then how
those pass signals up and you know turns
out that like like uh prediction error
signals need to be inhibitory but the
between column connections are all
glutamatergic and so they're excitatory
right so you need to basically have any
prediction are signal be excitatory but
then pass through some inhibitory inner
neuron at the receiving end to then turn
it into right an inhibitory thing and
then you know as opposed to the simple
kind of vanilla PR predictive coding
architectures or or algorithm um the
most of the canonical microser circuit
stuff has been pitched in terms of these
um more kind of like temporally extended
versions of predictive coding where you
have like at each level you're not just
representing a hidden state but you're
also representing what they call like a
hidden cause um and the the distinction
between hidden State and a hidden causes
is that like one of them actually
predicts the Dynamics of the states at
the level below um so it's kind of like
hidden state to say like hidden state is
or now I'm mixing up which one it is one
of them either hidden state or hidden
cause uh I mean this is just very
jargony just arbitrary choice of
terminology to a certain extent but but
well I'll say it the way that's a little
more intuitive to me but but so if it's
if hidden state is like birds singing a
song right at one level then you know I
just have some representation about you
know probability of bird singing song or
something like that fairly abstract but
then that then sends a signal to
represent this hidden cause thing and
what the hidden cause thing does is send
predictions down to the level below
about like some series of notes right
like in some sequence to the level where
the hidden State at that level is like
representing what note is happening at a
unit you know some at some time period
but so so even there right those are
both predictive coding but those are two
different predictive yeah different
predictive coding theories um so so
anyway I mean so just just to point out
fairly longwinded that there's just a
lot of complexity in in specifying what
you're in fact even testing um but the
um but the main the main thing I mean
the main kind of broad Strokes result
was just that um in predictive coding I
mean there's certainly nothing that
rules it out right I mean there's um
there's some cool you know results Pro
probably like the strongest results that
um would suggest something like that has
to be going on is um like findings
related to like emission responses right
where brain activity increases when you
expect to get a to get a stimulus and
the stimulus is absent yeah right so
like if a stimulus is stimulus comes
right it should trigger some activity
under a feedforward sort of hypothesis
but the absence of something should
never trigger yeah yeah classic shorts
and
monu
yeah but um but the but emission
responses and you know other things like
error related negativity and a lot of
the the kind of more standard stuff that
looks like prediction and prediction
eror responses that are consistent with
predictive coding um you know they
certainly don't you know provide really
precise evidence so there's like you
know particular Layer Two Three neurons
that are representing prediction errors
and five six ones that are going to pred
there are a couple cool studies that
have come out like super recently though
that do look like with like laminer fmri
and things like that that do are
starting to support these kind of like
distinct populations of eror neurons and
pric neurons so that stuff's exciting um
very well you know it's a niche but at
least it's it's incorporating well at
least it sounds like from your
investigation it's beginning to well I'd
like to think that it's beginning to
down on some specific ways that we can
get more precise hypotheses and ways of
testing those hypotheses I mean it's
it's it's it's read you know if the you
know fre the the main papers 2009
2010 fair enough that it's taken a
little while to get its you know it it
to get to start reaching that kind of
finer Precision that that that level of
granularity that level of I think you
know tomorrow some of that philosophical
work needed to be done just to lay out
exactly the parameters if you pardon the
P of the expandom of what we're trying
to find out so I don't know it sounds
promising to me sounds exciting yeah no
I mean I think yeah I mean certainly I
think I think we need to hold things to
a given I mean as you say right given
that these um you know these particular
theories are you know much more recent
right than other like you know
computational Neuroscience theories that
have had a lot more time right to be to
be tested um so so yeah I mean I think
we need to be fair given the amount of
time that that um you know these things
have been uh these things have even been
been around to test and the you know the
number of groups that have been
motivated to you know put together
studies and get them funded right to do
these sorts of tests um absolutely um
you know I mean and and with um and with
respect to uh you know active inference
I mean that's even more true right I
mean the the actual kind of like
empirically testable like behavioral
modeling you know sorts of you know
sufficient sufficiently precise right
formalisms for um you know like the kind
of stuffs that we do you know what's
that's been around like what since like
2017 is and and it's you know been kind
of evolving from there and and so um and
so you know much much less time even and
um you know I mean I think there's a lot
of things that you know I mean we still
need to do I mean along the approach
that we're taking right so I mean
primarily you know what we've you know
the stuff that we review that you know
that we've done with the you know empir
like trying to find empirical support
for active inference um probably hasn't
really up until now done a good enough
job of doing model comparison against
competing models you know our Focus has
been largely um kind of like
computational Psychiatry focused so the
idea has been more okay let's define a
set of active inference models fit those
models to behavior and see where we can
find differences in those models between
clinical groups and healthy groups right
so we can show that like in an absolute
sense right like active INF models could
explain data pre you know reasonably
well right like on a on a model on a
task where like chance action
probability would be like oneir you know
like these models can explain behavior
with you know assigning probabilities
around like you know between like0 65
and 7 something right so I mean it's
it's you know much much better than
chance and not uh not too different than
what you'd see in in other um
computational Neuroscience studies um
but you know that hasn't that doesn't
directly compare active inference models
um to you know other classes of models
right that have already been around
right and so that's a little bit more
the kind of thing we've been trying to
do recently is to more definitively kind
of say you know how much you know can we
find evidence for active inference
models that is not equal evidence for
other models that have been around for
longer yeah yeah yeah no that that it
sounds absolutely worthwhile and yeah I
think I think some people are you know
they don't they almost don't want to do
that because if it turns out that an RL
model does better than an active
inference model then like let's just
throw in the towel but um yeah even even
that I think needs to be kind of like
understood with a little bit of a grain
of salt though because because um well
you can you can worry that that um that
there are tasks where the tasks are
simple enough that an RL model will do a
perfectly good job explaining what's
going on and an active inference model
would basically predict the exact same
thing right right as a reinforcement
learning model and in that case you know
maybe the active inference model is more
complicated and so
like but you know I mean that's just
because in those contexts they're you
know they have a certain isomorphism you
know to them so I think I think you have
to you have to make these comparisons in
tasks where um like a a simpler model
certainly could explain behavior equally
well but but there's there's reason to
think other models that that there could
be the um patterns of Dynamics in the in
the choice behavior that um that could
differentiate right active inference
models from reinfor from reinfor I like
it Ryan I like it you're staying true to
the to the field I like it it's good
that loyalty is much needed but no I I I
I really do admire the the intellectual
rigor and the academic rigor it's um
it's much needed uh I wouldn't certainly
wouldn't want to like say you know like
our stuff and only our stuff I mean
there are other people that are doing
you know very recently that have been
doing really cool stuff like there's
this um like the first author last like
gson or something like that I can't
remember Sam gson Maybe I I don't quote
me on that but but they did this really
cool um um study where they took like
these two um a couple I remember it was
like
four I think it was yeah four different
like publicly available data sets um
from uh on the two-step task um twostep
tap is a very kind of classic um RL task
that like basically was designed
specifically to estimate how much people
are doing more kind of like modelbased
versus model free um sorts of planning
um and um and I mean Super widely used I
mean people have shown really cool stuff
with it you know like like
developmentally you know like kids as
they get older start to look more model
based you know right right right you
know basically means they actually start
to use an actual transition function
more right um um and um but um but you
know so what they did is they they took
right like the classic you know widely
used um modelbased model-free kind of
combo model that typically gets used for
um um for that task and then they also
fit that same data to um to uh um like a
competing active inference model um and
um in two of the four data sets
um model comparison was kind of
equivocal um and in the other two data
sets active inference models did win in
model comparison um for that and these
are pretty large data sets and again
that's a very it's another you know very
kind of classic task so the fact that uh
the fact that active inference did a
better job of explaining two-step tax
Behavior I thought you know I thought
that was actually like incredibly yeah
no well yeah I mean when it starts
better than what we've done in terms of
actually testing active inference models
yeah well when starts entering into the
space where others should dominate
that's you know that's when you know
it's onto something Ryan I know you're
you're you're the world's busiest man uh
filling out forms and and all sorts uh
and so I'm incredibly appreciative we've
just hit the hour and a half mark um
well thank you so much for for giving me
your time and educating me I feel I mean
every time I have people on whether
they're philosophers neuroscientists
mathematicians and so on it's always
such a pleasure to to learn more about
the work they're doing in terms of what
you've got coming up OB so this paper
that is coming out in the future uh
that's out people can read it although
it's supposedly out in the future um
what else what else have you got coming
up where can people find your work how
can people reach out to you if they're
interested in asking questions or
collaborating or whatever it might be oh
yeah I mean you know any anything on our
you know our lab website uh you know or
email me you know like R rsmith lur
institute.org you know feel free uh you
know we'll link the L Twitter I mean you
know any any know the typical Roots all
the all the standard the standard stuff
I mean my email is also typically the
one that's like the corresponding author
email on most papers so um you know
there's certainly Lots uh lots of ways
to get in contact me with you so desire
but great well we'll make sure we link
everything below uh so thank you once
again from me and The Institute it's
been really really fun sure no thank you
very much for having me